<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A treatise declaring and showing that images are not to be suffered in churches]</title>
            <title>Einigerle Bild. English</title>
            <author>Bucer, Martin, 1491-1551.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1535</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1386</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19961662</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19961662</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23564</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23564)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1717:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A treatise declaring and showing that images are not to be suffered in churches]</title>
                  <title>Einigerle Bild. English</title>
                  <author>Bucer, Martin, 1491-1551.</author>
                  <author>Bedrotus, Jacobus, d. 1541.</author>
                  <author>Marshall, William, fl. 1535.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Marshall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1535]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page lacking; title suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Running title: That pictures nor ymages ought to be worshipped.</note>
                  <note>"Tr. by W. Marshall from the Latin trans. by J. Bedrote of M. Bucer's Das einigerle Bild"--STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Publisher from colophon; date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: t.p. (sig. A1, p. [1]-[2]) lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Idols and images --  Worship.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:23564:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23564:1"/>
            <head>The preface.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>¶ All the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of them which at Argentoratum do preche and teache Chriſt / </signed>
               <salute>vnto the good and godly reders do wyſſh grace.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ycauſe our moſt noble and alſo moſte godlye Senatours dyde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue / that the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyons and manyfolde euyls / which haue ben hytherto by the reaſon of pyctures &amp; ymages / ar nat ſuffyciently taken away by the only exhortacyons of prechers. And agayne dyd conſydre / that it was nat poſſyble for any man to decree or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde any thing con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernynge them more wyſely / than god had preſcrybed &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in his lawe and prophetes: They decreed and ordeined &amp; gaue forth a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / that whatſoeuer pycture or ymages hath ben wont
<pb facs="tcp:23564:2"/> to be worſhypped in holye places / ſhulde both they and their aulters be clene taken away / and avoyded out of ſyght. Bycauſe .iiii. yeres ago / they had abrogated priuate maſſes / and a tweluemoneth a go foure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune and open maſſes. For fyrſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſultatyon and delybe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratyon of more pure ceremonyes to be brought into their places. Secondarily they lokinge for cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne counſels and aſſembles / of whiche it was hoped / that ſome what ſhulde be decreed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the generall reformation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che. And thyrdly the wekeneſſe of certayne parſones / whiche coulde nat yet ſe / how gret impyetie and abuſyon is in maſſes / hadde ſaued the reſydewe of maſſes. And they hadde ſuſpended theym vpon this condityon / that if any man coulde proue by the ſcryptures / that they
<pb facs="tcp:23564:2"/> were nat contrary to Chriſt / they ſhuld be reſtored againe euerione.</p>
            <p>Moreouer / ſeyng there ar many men / whiche do nat yet perceyue nor knowe / how moche theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges do hyndre fayth &amp; trew godly lyuynge: we do eaſely coniecture / that there are nat a fewe / whiche ſhall accompte this dede of oure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune wele / to be a folyſſhe and a wycked preſumption. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / for as moch as it is the dutye of all chriſten men / as moch as in them lyeth to gyue dilygence &amp; to prouyde / that the thynge whiche they haue godly done &amp; wrought / maye be accompted &amp; knowen of other men / to be none other wyſe than godly done. And alſo to take good hede / that no man may haue occaſyon worthely to ſpeke euyl of their goodneſſe (as Paule ſayth) Herefore we haue iudged it to be
<pb facs="tcp:23564:3"/> our parte and dutye which taught that the thynge ought to be done / which nowe our ſenate hath done in very dede / &amp; brought to paſſe ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry dilygently to ſhewe the cauſe of all this whole dede: but with as moche brefeneſſe as maye be / that if it wolde be / we might happely pacify &amp; apeaſe the myndes / at the leſt wyſe of ſome perſones / whom this buſines hath troubled &amp; gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſconte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted / &amp; doubteleſſe if we may optayn this one thyng (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is denyed to no man / be he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo gret a malefactour) that we maye haue the one eare open to here what we ſhall ſaye: We feare nat / but that whoſoeuer can fynde in their hertes / and abyde to know theſe fewe thinges / which we ſhall allege fyrſt out of holy ſcriptures. Secondarily of the writynges of the fathers. And thyrdly of the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crees
<pb facs="tcp:23564:3"/> of emperours agaynſt pyctu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res and ymages. If it be ſhewed alſo of whom / &amp; for what cauſe &amp; conſyderation both they were firſt brought vp in the churches of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten men / and alſo beynge defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded haue contynued in the ſame. We doute nat (I ſaye) but that all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che perſones: if it be ſo / that it be graunted vnto them to knowe the truthe / wyll alſo deſyre with vs / that this thynge whiche is done here with vs / all other churches of chriſten men / dyd folowe &amp; execute in lyke maner. Therfore we praye and beſeche all thoſe / whoſoeuer ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nat yet lyke nor alowe this our exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple (which thinge it is no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyle thoughe it happen to many men / if a man conſydre what thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges haue euerywhere goten ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gthe amonge Chriſten men) that they wyll voucheſafe to rede this
<pb facs="tcp:23564:4"/> ſhorte lytell treatyſe to the ende / which fyrſt was made in our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall tongue / and nowe by oure moſt welbeloued brother / Iames Bedrote / is tranſlated into laten. But let them fyrſte before they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne to rede / call for the ſpyrite of Chriſt / which only ledeth into all verytie and truth / &amp; that done let them than gyue ſentence of vs. Chriſt the ſauyour of mankynde graunt to all thoſe which bere his name / grace to reiecte all ſuche thi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges which do call away the mynd from him: that they maye lyfte vp their myndes vnto him ſyttynge in heuen / and worſhippe the father by him / in ſpiryte and truth. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:23564:4"/>
            <head>¶ That ymages wont to be wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipped / ar nat to be ſuffred in the churches of Chriſten men.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit / there are verye manye cauſes / whyche mighte ſuffycyently ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfy the myndes of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and perſwade them to take awaye images out of theire churches: yet no man wyll deny this cauſe to be without dout chefe and princypall / bycauſe it is forbydden in the fyrſte of goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes / that any maner of images ſhulde be had amonge his peple. For thus we rede in the ſcrypture:<note place="margin">Ex. 20</note> 
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">I am that euerlaſtyng god. I am thy god which haue de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuered the fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aegypt / the houſe of thraldom and bondage. Thou ſhalt haue no ſtraunge goddes be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſydes me. Thou ſhalt make vnto
<pb facs="tcp:23564:5"/> thy ſelfe no grauen or caruen ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / nor the ſymilytude of any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thinge which is aboue in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or beneth in the erth: nor of thoſe thynges whiche are in the waters vnder the erthe. Thou ſhalte nat bowe thy ſelfe before them / neither worſhip them: For I am thy lord god euerlaſting / ſtronge / &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty / punyſſhynge the fautes of the fathers in the chyldren / euen vnto the thyrd generatyon of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which do hate me. &amp; powringe forthe my goodnes / euen vnto the thouſanth generation of them which do loue me / and do obſerue &amp; kepe my com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes.</q> Lo / here are .ii. lawes of the lord ſet forth vnto the whiche natte without good cauſe amonge other / do chalenge vnto them ſelues the fyrſte place. The fyrſt of them requyreth of vs / that we do take this eternall and euer
<pb facs="tcp:23564:5"/> beinge god (ſo as he is in very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de) for oure god. The later doth nat only forbyd ſtraunge goddes / but alſo it forbyddeth bothe the y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of them / &amp; alſo of all other thynges / to be hadde amonge the people of god / vnto which people doutleſſe / that is to wytte vnto all true beleuers / all ſuch maner pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes do apperteyne. For theſe ar the trewe Iſraelyties / as it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the ſcryptures.<note place="margin">Rom. 2 iiii.ix. Gala. 3 iiij.</note> For Chriſt came nat to breke the lawe: but to fulfyll it fyrſt of any man. Nowe in very dede thei ar annexed to the lawe of god / &amp; alſo encloſed and conteyned in it / whatſoeuer thingꝭ do bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge any cauſe or occaſyon vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the loue of god or of the neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure / to ſhewe or put forth it ſelfe more and more.</p>
            <p>¶ In dede god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded very many thynges to his olde people
<pb facs="tcp:23564:6"/> whiche were greatly auaylable &amp; helpynge to the princypall poynte and ende of his lawe. But after that chriſt was ones exalted to the right hande of his father / and the holighoſt was ſent all abrode into the worlde / we ar delyuered &amp; free from a great parte of ſuche maner legall ceremonyes. As for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple it was goddes wyll &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / that the Iewes ſhulde lyue togyther by theym ſelues / abſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng from companyeng and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge with the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyles (for he dyd nat yet voucheſafe that they ſhuld haue knowlege of hys doctryne) to thente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / no dout of it / that they ſhulde by ſomoche / be the more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedyent to his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement / by how moche they were the leſſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted &amp; infected with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of the gentyls / worſhippyng falſe goddes. But after that / the wall
<pb facs="tcp:23564:6"/> which departed the one people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other was throwen downe / &amp; both the gentyls &amp; alſo the Iewes grewe togyther in to one people. This lawe whiche forfended the Iſraelytes / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panyenge with the gentyls / coulde do no ſeruyce nor profyte at all. wherfore it was con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenyent that it ſhulde be abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Suche another lyke thynge is cyrcumcyſyon / &amp; alſo the rytes &amp; ceremonyes of purifycations / the choyſe of metes / the diuerſyties of places &amp; perſones / &amp; whatſoeuer beſydes theſe is red to haue ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded in the olde lawe / concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge outwarde ſacryfyces. For theſe thynges in as moche as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fayth nor charytie doth nowe requyre them: it ſhalbe lawfull &amp; free for vs either to obſerue &amp; kepe them / orels to leue them vndone. For the trewe honoure &amp; worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge
<pb facs="tcp:23564:7"/> of god / which hath ben by the prechynge of the Apoſtels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly publyſſhed to the whole worlde / wyll in nowyſe ſuffre it ſelfe to be thruſte ſo narowly into ſuche maner ſtreyghtes of places / dayes / meates / and perſons.</p>
            <p>¶ But as concernynge ymages / the thyng is farre other wyſe: For theſe beynge ones forbidden muſt nedes ſtande alwayes ſtyll forbyd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den / ſpecyally for this cauſe. By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the trewe honouryng of god can nat be but either myniſſhed / or els dyuerſe wayes letted: as ſone as we ſhall ſuffre the ſayde yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / contrary to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god in churches / or in other pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces / where they be honoured or els maye be honoured. For ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall &amp; parfyte fayth / &amp; the parfyte honouryng of god requyreth / that we ſhulde do our dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:23564:7"/> this only god to be knowen in all places / that we ſhulde drede and honour him: that we ſhulde in all places and at all tymes with full mouth / prayſe &amp; magnify the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of him alone. But ymages ar ſo farre from helpynge vnto this thynge / that the ſame do dyuerſe wayes hyndre &amp; let euery man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trewe honouryng of god. For who is he (I beſeche you) whom ymages ſet vp in churches / or in other more narowe places / haue nat rather made neglygent about the trewe honouryng of god / than holpen him any whyt to honoure god trewly. Ye / moreouer (if it be lawfull to ſpeke the truth) the true honour of god / beynge ſubuerted and ouerthrowen / they haue quite blotted out of mennes myndes the remembrance of thoſe thinges / for whoſe cauſe it is fayned / that they
<pb facs="tcp:23564:8"/> were fyrſt ſet vp. And though it be ſo / that otherwhyles peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture by the occaſyon of theſe godly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monytours / ſome thought and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of god doth come into our mynde: yet the ſame thought is ſoner vanyſſhed away / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it can gether ſufficient rotes in the breſtes or myndes of men. For as it is but a thyng of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s deuiſyng / and receyued without the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of god: euen ſo was it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer able to moue or ſtere oure her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; myndes with the quycke &amp; lyuely perceyuynge / eyther of the workes or of the benefytes of god. By the reaſon of which thynge it hath come to paſſe / that no place hath ben lefte to the lyuely admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition / which is by the creatures of god: nat withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge that theſe ſayd creatures / bycauſe in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we do ſe them / &amp; handell them / 
<pb facs="tcp:23564:8"/> ought alſo in all places to ſtyre vp and renewe in vs the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of goddes infynite goodneſſe. Brefly / there is no cauſe / why we may more rightfully impute / ſhall I ſay or neglygence / or els our con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempte towardꝭ the trewe honour which is acceptable to god / vnto any other thynge than vnto ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. For after that theſe began to be worſhipped in certayne places / forthwith flowed in an vnmeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſee of all euyls. For though we paſſe ouer / that god by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon herof / was many wayes gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; diſpleaſed / bicau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to his ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; euydent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / nat only we haue wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipped the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but alſo puttyng our truſt in ſuch maner worſhippinge haue ꝑſwaded vnto oure ſelues / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> herewith we do wynne to our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues the fauour of god / &amp; truſtyng
<pb facs="tcp:23564:9"/> vnto theſe vayne &amp; tryflynge wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / haue either vtterly nat myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded / or at the leſtwyſe / haue loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly &amp; diſdaynefully done thoſe workes / with whiche only a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten mynde may be pleaſynge and acceptable to god. And who is he but he knoweth that by the reaſon herof / very many men haue ben ſo tycked with a merueylouſe vayne hope / to get of the lorde I wot nat what great hepes and treaſures of meritꝭ: that if thei had nat thought theſe maner tryfles to be moſte ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to god. Nat the goddeſſe Pitho herſelfe / <note place="margin">Pitho the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe of eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> with all her ſwete eloquence / ſhuld haue ben able to bringe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in mynde / beyng ſlowe inough / &amp; to moche vnto all other workes of charyte beſydes / to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue pleaſure to laſſhe oute ſo great rycheſſe / partly vpon the makyng and partely vpon the payntynge / 
<pb facs="tcp:23564:9"/> gyldynge / or otherwyſe garnyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhynge and deckynge of ymages.</p>
            <p>¶ Beſydes all this / I ſay (which is a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge more to be ſorowed for) this vayne honouryng of images hath engendred ſuch a confydence and truſt in a greate ſorte of men / that thoſe workes which ar in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dede good &amp; godly / layde clene a ſyde: they haue taken occaſyon to lyue a gret dele the more at lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and more lycentiouſly / bycauſe they ar perſwaded &amp; in ſtedfaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe / that with theſe workes they haue ſo gotten the fauour of god / that at all other ſynnes &amp; vyciouſe lyuynge / he doth wynke and wyll nat ſe them / &amp; as though hauynge lybertie graunted to ſynne vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed / they might gyue themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues at large to all maner vyces / e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as they lyſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. If this thynge were nat well inough kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen
<pb facs="tcp:23564:10"/> vnto all men by experyence: we coulde proue it with ſuche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner examples &amp; proufes / that euen he that were blynde / ſhuld percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue playnly / that ther hath nat lygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely any other more perilouſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe cropen into the churche / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this of honourynge ymages.</p>
            <p>¶ Who is he than / that doth nat here ſomwhat ſmell and perceyue the falſe wyly craftes of oure olde enemy / which hath neuer ceſſed to driue the worlde vnto ſuche mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe / that puttynge away the true honour of god / men ſhuld receyue and embrace this honour / whiche maketh them to go the cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary waye from god / diſceyuyng all maner men with the vayne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parence &amp; outward ſyght of yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / as though (god wot) men by them were put in remembrance of godly thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / whan in very dede
<pb facs="tcp:23564:10"/> by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge els hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought in / but an innumerable hepe of all euyls. Moreouer / that man / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heuen / erth / &amp; whatſoeuer is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in them / &amp; moſte ſpecyally man / which is created to the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of god / fynally whom god him ſelfe / the worker of all theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / doth nat waken &amp; ſtere vp to loue him &amp; prayſe him: no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he be madder than a man of Bedlem / wyll beleue that this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll be moued greatly with deed and vnſenſyble images. Yf ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny workes of god / if ſo many crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures / no leſſe profytable than mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueylouſe / whiche ſet the goodneſſe of god before thyne eyes / can nat enflame the / thou arte doutleſſe to vnſenſyble for to be admonyſſhed and ſtyrred euer of vnſenſyble y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages. The goodneſſe of god ſhi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth &amp; appereth in all his creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.
<pb facs="tcp:23564:11"/> There is nothynge / but it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth god hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf. All y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world is full of thinges / which do nat ceſſe to put vs in remembrance of oure duty / that is to wyt / that we ſhuld contynue to be vnto other men / as god is vnto vs / &amp; that we ſhulde reſemble him by a certaine endles goodneſſe. But verily that thys thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hath the leſſe eſely be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought to paſſe hitherto / we maye thanke ymages for a gret parte therof: for ſuche expenſes which ought to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ben made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poore nedy folke (whom as beynge the very lyue i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of god / it was conuenyent to haue ſocoured &amp; made our fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des with our lyberalyte) we haue waſtfully beſtowed vpon ſtockes and ſtones. you ſe therfore that the trew honour / &amp; that which only is accepted to god / hath ben by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſo moch backed &amp; hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred
<pb facs="tcp:23564:11"/> as it hath by the vayne ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of images: &amp; that the deuil bi theſe craftes hath brought i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of god / the ouerthrowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of faith a more large lybertie to do whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer one lyſt vnpunyſſhed / falſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fydence in merytes / lothfulneſſe to exercyſe charite towardes our ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours: brefly in excedynge greate hepe of all maner euylles hath ben brought in: &amp; to make an ende / a wyndowe opened to all maner vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce &amp; ſynne: which thinge although it might be eſely ꝓued by exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples out of no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre: yet at this <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſent tyme let one exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the kingꝭ of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell ſuffyce. For howe many ſo euer of thoſe kyngꝭ thiſtorie of the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doth nombre among wycked &amp; vngodly ꝑſons / the ſame kyngꝭ it doth recorde to haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters &amp; worſhippers of ymages. on the other ſyde agayne / who ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:23564:12"/> ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended for their loue and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſe of vertue &amp; godlyneſſe: they wolde gyue euydent teſtymonie &amp; wytneſſe by diſtroyenge &amp; ryddi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ymages ſhortly out of the way / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were ruled by the holy ghoſt / and coulde nat but hate all maner thynges / whiche are abhomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſyght of god.</p>
            <p>¶ And as for that which ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do fayne / that ymages are the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of laye men. (For ſo they ſay) it is nat onely a weyke reaſon / but alſo a folyſſhe: as who ſhulde ſay / that god / of all moſte wyſeſt / and which is very wyſdome it ſelf / ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dyd nat know theſe bokes / or els through malyce dyd withhold from his owne people ſuch maner bokes &amp; monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / wherby they might be put in remembraunce of godly thinges. Forſoth it is a wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked thynge / euen ones to thynke / 
<pb facs="tcp:23564:12"/> that god (which accordyng to his goodnes towardes vs / lefte none of thoſe thynges vnſhewed / &amp; as they ſay / poynted with his fynger which might helpe to further &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the knowlege of him ſelfe / &amp; to ſtyrre vs vp alſo to the loue of him ſelfe) I can nat tell of what euyll wyll &amp; hatred had kepte this worſhippynge of ymages fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne people. For nat only he dyd nat teche the worſhippinge of ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges / but alſo he dyd with expreſſe and playne wordes vtterly forbyd it / as it appereth euydently by the fyrſte lawe of all. Nowe what is more vnreaſonable and vnlykely / than if the vſe of ymages be ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytable / as theſe men do fayne it to be / that god dyd nothynge eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me theym / ſeynge that in the mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſeaſon he had begon to tech his people / beynge yet but yonge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners
<pb facs="tcp:23564:13"/>
/ &amp; haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g but ſmall knolege with ſo many outward thinges / e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as one ſhuld enduce a chylde / ſeing alſo that he wold his workꝭ and benefytes to be openly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſo many wonderfull myracles / and by ſo manyfolde ceremonies, beſydes this / dyd induce the peple with holydayes / &amp; other rytes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable. Fynally lefte nothing behynde to the ſhadowing &amp; fygu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe of himſelfe largely vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I ſay / how fortuned it / if ymages be ſo ꝓfytable / that god for al this inſomoch dyd nothinge eſteme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he wold in no wiſe ſuffre them to be amonge his people. Syth than it is ſo / that it was nat lauful for the people / which was yet rude and ignorante to haue any maner ymages / althoughe the lorde dyd by many other dyuerſe ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es by lytle &amp; lytle teche and facyon
<pb facs="tcp:23564:13"/> the ſame people. Howe moch leſſe ſhall it be lawfull for vs / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truthe ſucceded in to the place of ſhadowes / hathe nowe made free frome outwarde ceremonies / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyryng non other honour or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce of vs / than that whiche ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in ſpirit and truth.</p>
            <p>¶ Let vs therfore haue ymages / nat of ſtone / nat of wood / nat gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen / or caſt in any moulde (al whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che god hath ones for euer forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den / as well to vs / as to the Iues) But let vs rather conſyder the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye worde of god / let vs occupye and buſye oure ſelues in it bothe night and daye: Beſydes this / let all the whole frame of this world be vnto vs amonument and token to put vs in remembrance of god / that whatſoeuer trewe godlyneſſe is remaynynge in vs / it maye nat by the workes of men / but by the
<pb facs="tcp:23564:14"/> workes of god wel &amp; after a godly facyon conſydre / enflame &amp; kyndle vs to the prayſyng &amp; louyng of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>¶ Nowe as touchyng to this rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon / that ſome men do make for to excuſe the vſe of ymages / bycauſe (as they ſay) after that god taki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the nature of man vpon him / had voucheſafed to lyue amonge men / and to be nayled faſt to the croſſe / and wylled the knowlege of him ſelfe to be egall publyſſhed and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared vnto all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: there is no cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe why it ſhulde nat be lawfull to vſe ymages / but yet moſt ſpecyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Chriſt crucifyed / to thentent that we might oftentymes be put in remembrance / how by his deth we haue gotten redemptyon &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatyon. Verily we do nat denye / whatſoeuer holſome &amp; profytable thinge hath come to vs by the deth of Chriſt / which he ſuffryng wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:23564:14"/> he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſaunte amonge men / reconſyled ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kinde to his father: yet that natwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng the ſame Chriſt dyd playnly wytneſſe / that his bodily preſence was nothynge profytable.<note place="margin">Ioa. vi</note> It is the ſpyrit (ſayth he) that quyckeneth. It was ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for our profyte / that he ſhulde bodily departe from vs.<note place="margin">Io. xvi</note> And for that cauſe after his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he aſcended vp into heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the right hande of his father / to thende that he might cary vs alſo vp to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me place / if it be ſo that we haue ryſen with him by fayth.<note place="margin">Col. iij</note> Beſydes this / whan Paule / accordynge to the ſame ſentence / dothe openly e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaye / that he doth no lengre know Chriſt / as touchinge the fleſſhe: he ſygnifyeth that another maner of worſhippynge is requyred of vs / that is to wyt / a ſpirytuall honour and ſuche one / which may effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:23564:15"/> and ſtrongly tranſforme oure hertes / which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſyth it can nat be done by the benefyte &amp; helpe of ymages / let vs ſaye a due for euer to theſe tryfelynge &amp; vnprofytable helpes / which ar rather hynderers of true fayth &amp; godly lyuynge / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; tokens to put vs in remembraunce of godly thynges. It is vndoutedly ſtarke madneſſe to deſyre to be put in remembrance of the benefytes of Chriſt by ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / whan Chriſt him ſelfe ought to worke the ſame in our myndes / whiche in vs &amp; all creatures wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all thinges. Let vs (I ſaye) haue this Ieſus nayled faſte vpon the croſſe / ſet vp before the eyes of oure mynde / as oftentymes as he tryeth vs / &amp; layeth his croſſe vpon vs / by pacyence of trybulations &amp; aduerſyte. Let Chriſt ſo poſſeſſe &amp; fyll the breſt of a chriſten man / of
<pb facs="tcp:23564:15"/> whom he hath his name / that ther be no thinge / but it do put him in remembrance of his lorde / the crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour &amp; maker / the gouernour / and the ſauyour / &amp; preſeruer of al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Wherfore ſo oftentymes as he loketh vp towardes the ſkye / he can nat chuſe but remembre forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with his ſauyour Chriſte / whiche raygneth aboue all heuens on the right hande of his father. As ſone as he beholdeth the ſonne / by &amp; by he thinketh vpon Chriſt the ſonne of rightuouſnes / &amp; the lyght of the worlde / whiche with his beames lyghteneth the herte. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſeeth a man / he remembreth that Chriſt was made man for our ſake. If he do met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with a kynge or a prince / anon Chriſt the kyng of kynges / and lorde of lordes / is in hys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. Whan he hereth any precher or techer / lo / ſtreight ways
<pb facs="tcp:23564:16"/> his mynde is vpon Chriſte the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly doctour and maiſter: as the garment done vpon the body doth the body both profyte &amp; honeſtye: euen ſo doth a godly mynde thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke that Chriſt is the very weddynge garment / whom all thoſe perſons haue done on theym ſelues / howe many ſoeuer haue ben baptyſed. A chriſten man neuer eteth or drin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth / but forthwith he is put in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance that chriſt is the only and the very meate / which fedeth and nouryſſheth vs into eternall lyfe. If at any tyme he doth occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye water / forthwith it cometh to his mynde / that Chriſt is the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne / out of which we may draw drinke agaynſt vnſaciable thurſt. Brefly / ſo oftentymes as he ſhall ſee either a ſhepe or a ſhepherde / a gate / a way / a vynetree / or a ſtone / forthwith he conceyueth an image
<pb facs="tcp:23564:16"/> and ſymilytude of his lorde chriſt which wyllyngly ſuffred him ſelfe to be ſlayne &amp; offred vp for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concylyation of the worlde / which boſteth him ſelfe to be a good ſhep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herde / whiche is the waye and the yate / by whiche men go &amp; entre in to heuen / which wytneſſeth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe to be the trewe vynetre / the corner<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtone / &amp; ſet for a foundatyon. Fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally / if thou before vxed with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſyte / orels ſeeſt any other man to be in afflyction &amp; calamyte: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes this / if thou be troubled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> paſſyons &amp; noughtye affectyons &amp; deſyres: forthwith (if there be any percell of Chriſte in the) ſet afore the eyes of thy mynde / bothe the deth &amp; the reſurrectyon of Chriſt / &amp; ſtedfaſtly and depely conſydre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / by the meanes wherof thou maiſt in ſuche wyſe arme and fence thy mynde with complete harneſſe / ſo
<pb facs="tcp:23564:17"/> ſure and ſo full of moſte effectuall conſolations / that thou ſhalt be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble caſely to abyde and ouercome whatſoeuer aduerſytie ſhall fall vnto the. So than if after this maner &amp; facyon we wold haue luſt and pleaſure to lerne Chriſte par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytely in all thinges / &amp; his workes with a certaine lyuely felynge and iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the minde / which ſhuld tranſforme &amp; chaunge vs: without dout the loue of god ſhuld be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueylouſly augmented in vs / &amp; we ſhulde alſo (as it were in a glaſſe) ſee / with what comlyneſſe / &amp; after what maner &amp; facyon the courſe of this lyfe ought to be paſſed ouer &amp; brought to an ende / which thinge none ymages can euer be able to teache vs. For theſe (whatſoeuer manerons they be) can nat ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thyne eyes any ſymilytude of god: but rather with avayne ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynation
<pb facs="tcp:23564:17"/> whan thou weneſt that thou arte warme with a certayne hote loue &amp; deſyre / to conſydre and thynke vpon godly thinges: ſoden<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly this heate &amp; feruentneſſe vaniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth awaye / and it ſhall make the more neglygent to all trew workꝭ ſemely for a chriſten man / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer thou waſt before. We do therefore pituouſly diſceyue our own ſelues with this flyeng deuotion / as thei call it. For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue thought our ſelues to be fed &amp; full of the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter thinges: we fynde by expery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence / ſooner than we wolde haue thoughte / that we haue ben fedde with wynde (as it is ſayde in the prouerbe) and that we are emptye and voyde of meate / whiche doth nouryſſhe and make fatte in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and godly lyuynge.</p>
            <p>¶ But as for theſe perſones / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che truſtynge and berynge theym
<pb facs="tcp:23564:18"/> ſelues bolde vpon the law of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten lybertie / doo excuſe ymages / ſayenge / that for this cauſe they ar nat vnlawfull / bycauſe we maye vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lawfully at our owne ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure / as well as we may other out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward thinges / &amp; therfore that it is better y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there be images of Chriſt than to haue ymages of prophane thynges: I wolde that theſe men ſhuld fyrſt lerne / that whatſoeuer ymages are honoured or maye be honoured / ar nat to be compted in the nombre of outward thinges / &amp; therfore they ar vſed both to the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iury of the diuyne maieſty / which only ought to be honoured / &amp; alſo to the labefactation &amp; decay of the fayth. There is no cauſe therfore why the conſyderation of chriſten lybertye / maye ſuffre in any wyſe ſuche maner ymages. For the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of a Chriſten man / is nat a
<pb facs="tcp:23564:18"/> lycence to do what ſoeuer he lyſte / but it is rather a voluntary execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vertuouſe workes / which ar done by the motyon of charytie / &amp; nat by the commaundemente and compulſyon of the lawe.</p>
            <p>¶ Nowe as touchyng the obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon of ſome men / that there is no cauſe why it maye nat be lawfull for vs to vſe pyctures &amp; ſtandynge ymages. For lykewyſe as wyſe men / &amp; thoſe perſones which haue ben ſuffyciently inſtructed in the trew doctryne &amp; fayth of Chriſt / ar nothing offended nor do take any hurte by images: euen ſo weke per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones / and ſuche as be nat yet well ſkylled in godlye thinges / eyther whan they haue better inſtruction and are taught the truthe / ſhall be nothynge hurte by the reaſon of y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages / or if they be ſturdy &amp; ſuch as wyll nat be taught / they ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:23564:19"/> no whyt better / though all images were clene taken away. So than neither for the weke perſons cauſe neither for their cauſe whiche are parfyte / is it neceſſarye to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye ymages. Doutleſſe / whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer with ſuche forked reaſons do coueyte to defende &amp; mayntayne i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages: they haue nat verye well conſydered nor waied the counſell and entent of Paule / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith<note place="margin">i Co. ix</note> 
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">All thynges ar laufull for me: but all thynges are nat expedyent nor profytable. All thynges ar laufull to me: but all thynges do nat edy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye.</q> And agayne in another place <q rend="margDblQuotes">knowlege maketh a man proude / but charyte doth edify.</q>
               <note place="margin">i. Co. 8</note> Alſo <q rend="margDblQuotes">there is no knowlege in all men.</q> And agayne: <q rend="margDblQuotes">Take hede that your ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye be nat an occaſyon of offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe and hurte to them which ar we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke.</q>
               <note place="margin">i. Co. 8</note> We do nat ſaye / naye verily:
<pb facs="tcp:23564:19"/> but that there is nothynge / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che letteth Images to be hadde / ſo that they be natte worſhypped.<note place="margin">j. Co. 8</note> We do graunte alſo / that caruers and paynters crafte / are craftes both gyuen by god / and alſo law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. But ſyth it is ſo that in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches euery were / ymages are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured / and namely roodes. It is nat poſſyble though thou prech neuer ſo ofte / nor neuer ſo erneſtly vnto the people / that ymages are nat to be honoured: but that there wyll be ſome / whiche wyll hold on ſtyl to put of their cappes vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> orels to lowte and make curteſye to them. For ſuche is the ſtrength of an olde rooted cuſtome / and the deuyll agayne exercyſeth and put<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth forthe his craftes &amp; diſceytes ſo buſely / that they which be ones ſnarled in his bondes / wyll neuer refrayne from worſhippinge of y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,
<pb facs="tcp:23564:20"/> Now both the occaſyons and alſo the prouocations &amp; entiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of al ſuch maner euyls muſt nedes be taken awaye / if ymages were ones put downe. And albeit truth it is / whiche they ſaye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menly / that where this vayne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſyon of images is nat plucked out of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes myndes by the word of god / there can nat the ſame be taken awaye neither by puttynge downe of ymages: yet is it nat ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerally trew / ſo that we may thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it to be trewly ſayde by all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner men indyfferently / as moch by one as by another. For by wicked men you maye well and truly ſay the ſame / which contynue always lyke to them ſelues / &amp; chaunge nat their mynde / whether thou doeſt with wordes make playne the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homynation of ymages with wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des orels doſt in very dede ryd all
<pb facs="tcp:23564:20"/> ymages oute quyte of ſyght. But to them that are weke / &amp; in whom there is remaynynge any / be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo lytell ſparke of godly loue and reuerence: it ſhall nat be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profytable nor in vaine / to witnes and confyrme their doctryne with their dede / that is for to ſaye / after that thou haſt diſcrybed &amp; paynted ymages ſo as they oughte to be with theyr owne coloures / boro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed of the ſcrypture / than dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to prouide / that the ſame alſo be ryd oute of mennes ſyght. For by that dede weke men ſhalbe con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyrmed / as in other thinges / ſo ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewyſe in this. For thy techynge ſhalbe all in vayne \ vnleſſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of thy dede do forthwith fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe / which ſhall cauſe thy doctri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to be of ſtrength and auctoryte. Paule doutles thought it nat ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient that the Corinthians knewe<note place="margin">j. Co. 8</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:23564:21"/> an idole to be nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: but he wold alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame people ſhuld i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any wyſe abſteyne from etynge of the meates offred to idoles / and that for the weke perſones ſake / to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> full knowlege of ſuche maner thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges was natte yet gyuen. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he badde the Corinthyans to confyrme and fortifye this doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne with the auctoritye of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / and to refrayne nat onely from eatynge of the fleſſhe offred vp in ſacrifyce to idoles: but alſo from all maner thynges that might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere euyll / or anye maner waye mighte offende weke perſones.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">i. Co. 9</note>For albeit he gaue them leaue to eate all maner fleſſhe / euen that alſo whiche was offered to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / if it were ſolde in the fleſſhe market: yet in the churches where they were offred vppe to ydoles / 
<pb facs="tcp:23564:21"/> he wolde in no wyſe graunte them lybertye to eate ſuche metes.</p>
            <p>Euen lyke wyſe do we iuge / that it is to be thought of images / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lykewyſe / as peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ſom man maye haue at home within his owne houſe / ſo that it be done without offendynge of his neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure: euen ſo the vſe of theym in churches or in other places / where either they maye be worſhypped or offende &amp; hurt their neyghbour is no wyſe longer to be ſuffred.</p>
            <p>Paule douteleſſe had leuer neuer eate fleſſhe in all his lyfe / than to gyue hys brother occaſyon to be offended:<note place="margin">i. Co. 8</note> And ſhall we all care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe wynke at ſo many occaſyons bothe of offenſyons and alſo of y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrye.<note place="margin">Mat. v</note> If Chriſte dothe byd the eye to be plucked oute of the
<pb facs="tcp:23564:22"/> heed / which is an obſtacle &amp; impe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyment to vs: how moch more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought pyctures and ymages to be plucked out of churches / by which we do nat only offende weke par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones / but alſo do ſette forthe oure relygyon to be ſcorned &amp; euyl ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of amonge the Turkes &amp; iues which do conuince vs / that in this behalfe we do agaynſt the princy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall poyntes of the chriſten fayth. Wolde god that with this ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition &amp; vayne honourynge of y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages we dyd nat ſtoppe &amp; kepe awaye a great menye bothe of the iewes and alſo of the Turkes / fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receyuynge and takinge of the cry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten fayth vpon them.</p>
            <p>¶ Now / if any man wyl obiecte that for the abuſe (which peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture no man wyll denye) ymages are nat altogyther to be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away (for els the ſouper of the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:23564:22"/>
/ and baptyme / with many other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / which ar encombred with dyuerſe abuſes / ought alſo in lyke maner to be abrogated) this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere we do make vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: That chriſten men ſhulde nat wynke at any abuſe / &amp; therfore whatſoeuer is brought into the church / contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to ſcrypture / it is to be amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded / &amp; to be tryed by the ſquyer &amp; rule of goddes worde / if any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge doth nat agree with it / it is to be cut away / with all ſpede that may be. And onely that thinge / which is right / whiche is holeſome / is to be reſtored to his owne place / and taken in his owne place / ſpecyally in the ſouper of the lorde / in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme / &amp; other thinges alſo whiche haue ben inſtytuted by the lorde. But ymages ar all maner wayes to be taken awaye / nat only for the abuſes / but moch more for the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:23564:23"/> of god / to which they ar play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne contrarye and repugnaunte. For we can nat ymagyn anye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner vtylitie / which may be ſayd to haue come by the reaſon of yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. On the other ſyde / that the ſuperſtityon of images doth draw with it an hepe of all euylles: we haue here to fore declared.</p>
            <p>¶ To make ſhorte / god neuer for bad any of thoſe thinges / wherof any commodytie or profyte might ryſe: but rather whatſoeuer thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge is profytable / and maye make vs better / he taught full largely / as wytneſſeth Paule verye euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently .ii. Timoth. iii.</p>
            <p>¶ But if any folyſſhe wyſe man doth thynke / that ymages ar ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nat to be taken awaye / bycau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe he fereth that thoſe weake per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones / which now ſuperſticiouſly
<pb facs="tcp:23564:23"/> do worſhippe / ymages / wolde be offended with the puttinge downe of ymages: this man douteleſſe / whyles he goth aboute to auoyde from the ſmoke (as it is ſayde in the prouerbe) is fallen into the fla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myng fyre. For whyles he feareth to offende diſperate perſons: with hurtefull offenſyons of ymages / he backeth and hindreth better me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche haue begonne to ronne the waye of the lorde withoute anye tournynge agayne.</p>
            <p>Who ſo euer dothe this / ſhall be gyltye of that cryme / of whiche Paule accuſeth Peter / in the epy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Galatyans.<note place="margin">Gala 2</note> For Peter whyles he was afrayde to offende certayne Iewes of Hieruſalem at Antyoche / and for that cauſe wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de natte vſe the lybertye of etyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge all maner meates / as he was wonte to doo before: Paule with
<pb facs="tcp:23564:24"/> ſtode him to his face in the preſens of the whole multytude / bycauſe he walked nat the ryȝt way / accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the truth of the goſpell. For as moch as was in him with his vnwyſe deſyre to auoyde offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge of the Iewes / he febled the right fayth / &amp; alſo nouryſſhed the incredulyte and vnbelefe of them / whom he ſtudyed to pleaſe in the meane ſeaſon. Brefly he dyd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge els / than whyles he wente about vnwyſly to auoyde one ieo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perdy / he caſt hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe into twayne. Doutleſſe after this maner to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre to auoyde occaſyons of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyons / is the full cauſe of offenſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And wold god it were nat of ſo great ſtrength as it is / amonge very many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now in theſe days. For a man ſhall ſe very many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which bycauſe they wold ymagen ſome honeſt cloke and coloure of
<pb facs="tcp:23564:24"/> their vnbelefe / do fayne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues bothe to do &amp; alſo to eſchewe very many thinges / leſt they might gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue any man occaſyon to be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: whan in very dede, they do it rather forcauſe to kepe the croſſe of Chriſt from theym ſelues. For with this fayned deſyre to wynne certayne curable ꝑſons / they ſhifte wel for them ſelues / that they may neither haue the euyll wyll of deſperate perſones / neitheir any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure or hurte done vnto them by the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We do nat denye ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily / that ſuch maner of doctryne &amp; lyuynge is moſt to be embraced &amp; folowed / whiche is an obſtacle or lettynge ſo no man / which doth purpoſely angre no man / whiche doth tourne no mannes mynde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from the truthe: yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe dilygence ought to be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the meane ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> luſtely / that
<pb facs="tcp:23564:25"/> none of thoſe thynges be lefte of / wherby the glorye of god and the helth of our neyghbours / may be furthered &amp; encreaſed. <q rend="margDblQuotes">Chriſt him ſelfe is the ſtone of offenſyon / the ſauyour of deth to deth / vnto them whiche are foreordeyned to lyfe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ After that we oure ſelues doe knowe the wyll &amp; pleaſure of the lorde: we muſt dilygently labour that other men alſo maye lyke and prayſe the ſame / &amp; that other men alſo maye haue luſte and pleaſure to confyrme theym ſelues vnto the ſame / yf we can nat obtayne thys / than oughte we rather to forſake father &amp; mother / &amp; al our goodes: ye / moreouer to renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce our owne ſelues / than to reſyſt or grudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wyll &amp; pleaſure of god But moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely we ſe it come to paſſe / that a great parte of men haue leuer both to get &amp; to mayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne
<pb facs="tcp:23564:25"/> and kepe the fauour of men with the miniſſhement of goddes honour: albeit yet it were better to wyn both the fauour of god / and alſo of men / with honeſt maners / and honeſt lyuyng / and with redy deſyre &amp; wyll to do good vnto all men / if we wolde begyn this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wynnynge the fauour of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and in other thinges wold lyue in this worlde fauteleſſe / as nere as we coulde / douteles there ſhulde be no man ſo parcyall in iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / but he wolde by and by gather in mynde / that it was neither preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuouſlye nor without good cauſe done of vs that we haue baniſſhed pictures and ymages cleane oute of churches. But whereto ſhulde we make many wordes / ſyth it is euident inough now / that images do miniſſh the true honour of god and that it is nat poſſyble but that
<pb facs="tcp:23564:26"/> weke men be gretly offended / and do take moche hurte by them. For they I meane weke perſones wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de paſſe lytell vppon the takynge awaye of ymages / if they were taught playnly / for what conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and ſkyll they were taken awaye. On the otherſyde / if they be nat taken away / forthwith they conceyue an opinyon / as thoughe it were nat lawfull to put them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Nowe as for obſtynate and vncurable perſones / nat onely we can nat with ſauing images bring theym to goodneſſe: but alſo with our ſufferaunce and ſlackneſſe we ſhall confyrme and eſtablyſſhe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the more in ydolatrye.</p>
            <p>¶ Brefely / if thou haſte ſo great deſyre and loue to wynne manye men to thy lorde: ordre thy lyfe ſo that other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may in very dede ſe experyence &amp; proufe / that Chriſt is
<pb facs="tcp:23564:26"/> alyue in the / and that all thy dedes and ſayengꝭ do breth and ſauoure of him. Withoute doubte / if thou wylte ordre thy ſelfe in this wyſe / thou ſhalt cauſe euen wicked men alſo / that they can nat chuſe / but at the leſt wyſe cloſely in their her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes confeſſe (their conſcyence dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge theym thervnto) that thou waſt nat only moued / but alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by the zele of god to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye images. And though in the meane ſeaſon / manye thynges be wantynge in vs: yet that natwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandynge we oughte to be neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe dilygent / to prouyde that all ſuche maner thinges be putte awaye / whiche ſoeuer are repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte to the worde of god.</p>
            <p>Let vs take no thoughte for anye maner thynge / which may caſt vs out any maner way of the fauoure of men: &amp; let vs go ſtreyght forth / 
<pb facs="tcp:23564:27"/> and take the nexte waye to fulfyll the rule of a Chriſten mans lyfe. for a true Chriſten man / although he doth in many thinges acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege him ſelfe to be a ſynner (as he is i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very dede) yet doth he neither alowe nor excuſe any maner thing which doth minyſſhe or deface the honour of his lord &amp; maiſter chriſt</p>
            <p>¶ Of the abuſe of ymages we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſpoken ſomewhat here to fore. But if any man do ſomwhat dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently conſyder &amp; way the mater / he ſhall perceyue vndoutedly / that ymages ar falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a farre gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abuſe amonge Chriſten men / than euer was amonge any hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then men. Images haue gyuen anſweres w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs / they haue wepte / one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath ben thoughte more holy and of more power than ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther. One more louely &amp; more gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tious than another / a man ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:23564:27"/> fynde ſome / whiche in a certayne place haue ſhewed forth their pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er in workyng of miracles / whan they haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tranſlated &amp; remoued into another place / they haue ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to do the ſame. Of the ymage at Lauretum / and dyuerſe other / ſyth the mater is knowen wyll i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe: we nede nat to ſaye any thynge at all. And I praye you / howe moche rycheſſe in the meane ſeaſon hath this ſuperſtition of y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages gathered togyther / nat w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out plentuouſe occaſyon of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyons: which ſayd ryches the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony &amp; pompe of a ſort of vnthrifty idle belyes hath deſtroyed &amp; waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully conſumed. In as moch ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / as trewe / full / &amp; parfyte faith can nat ſuffre ſo great abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon / &amp; ſyth it can nat be plucked vp by the rootes with the worde a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lone (For with the goodly &amp; glori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſe
<pb facs="tcp:23564:28"/> apperaunce of holyneſſe / and alſo by the reaſon of long cuſtome and contynuance / it hath gotten ſo great auctoryte &amp; eſtymation to it ſelfe) it is to be put awaye by the dede ſelfe. And wherto nedeth it to ſuffre thoſe thingꝭ amonge chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten men / whiche as they can nat but engendre euylles out of nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre / ſo can they cauſe no hope nor lokynge of anye maner profyte to come by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto any man. It dyd become vs chriſten men moſt of al to be moued &amp; ſtyred with the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of god / which doth ſo playnly and ſo expreſſely forbyd all maner of ymages. Whatſoeuer is redde concernynge ymages in the lawe / in the Prophettes / in the Pſalmes dothe moche more rightefully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayne vnto vs / whiche are tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte by Chriſte / that god is to be worſhipped in ſpyrite and truthe / 
<pb facs="tcp:23564:28"/> and that Chriſte alſo is natte to be honoured in Images of woode / of ſtone / or of ſyluer: but that he is to be worſhypped raither ſyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge on the right hande of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / and that all the membres of the ſayde Chriſt / that is to wytte / oure neyghbours are to be focou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with dedes of charytie.</p>
            <p>¶ And theſe fewe thinges amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge manye / it hathe lyked vs to borowe of the ſcryptures againſt pyctures and images / which ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures alone / a chriſten man hathe regarde vnto / as vnto the ſhote ankre / in all thynges / both whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ar to be deſyred / and alſo whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are to be eſchewed. But yet bycauſe it can nat be but pleaſure and conforte to the ſame Chriſten man / whatſoeuer either doctryne or exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples he ſhal fynde in the ſain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of god / which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſonant and
<pb facs="tcp:23564:29"/> agreyng to the ſcriptures: we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thought it expedient to brynge forth a fewe thynges of the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngꝭ of the fathers / by which the godly reder ſhall eaſely perceyue / that the apoſtles / martyrs / and all the beſt lerned &amp; moſt auncyent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers taught the ſame thinge / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is ordeyned &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded by the word of god / vntyll ſuch tyme as by the Gothyans &amp; the Vanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyanes / the chriſten faythe and the more pure knowlege of the truthe began to be gretly miniſſhed and brought in decay. For in the tyme of ſaynte Hieronymie / &amp; certayne yeres after him / we doo nat rede / that any byſſhop beynge of wyſe iugemente / dyd ſuffre pyctures or images in the churches of chriſten men. Of whiche thynge Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius / the moſte holy byſſhoppe of Salamine / in the yle of Cyprus
<pb facs="tcp:23564:29"/> ſheweth an euydent exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple in his epyſtel to Iohan the byſſhoppe of Hieruſalem / which epyſtel ſaynte Hieronyme tranſlated into latyn. For thus he writeth:<note place="margin">Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</note> whan we wente togyther to the holye place which is called Bethell / to make a collectyon there for poore people with the / accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to the cuſtome and maner of the churche: and I was come vnto the vyllage which is called Anablatha / &amp; as I paſſed by / dyd ſe a burnynge lampe / &amp; I had aſked what place it was / and had lerned that it was a churche / and had entred into it to praye: I dyd fynde there a vayle hangynge in the churche dores / coloured and paynted / &amp; hauynge as it were the ymage of Chriſt / or of ſome ſaynt (For I do nat wel reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre whoſe ymage it was) I ſay whan I had ſene that in the churche of Chriſt / 
<pb facs="tcp:23564:30"/> ther dyd ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the ymage of a man agaynſt the auctoritie of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: I dyd cut it / &amp; gaue counſel rather to the kepers of that place / that they ſhulde wynde ſome pore man that were deed / &amp; bury him in it. And they agayne grudgynge / ſayd by me: If he had mynded to cutte it / it was reaſon &amp; right that he ſhuld gyue another vayle and chaunge this / which thinge whan I had herde / I promyſed that I wolde gyue one / and ſende it forth with. Howbeit I deferred the ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding of it ſomwhat the longer / by the reaſon that I entended for to ſende a very good vaile in the ſted of it / &amp; I thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhulde haue had one ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto me out of Ciprus. Nowe I haue ſent ſuche one as I coulde get / &amp; I pray you / that you wyll byd the preeſtes of that ſame place / to receyue this vayle of the
<pb facs="tcp:23564:30"/> bringer / which we haue ſent / and afterwardꝭ to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde / that no mo ſuche maner vayles / which ar contrary to our relygyon / be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen vp in the churche of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Lo / here the ſentence of the mooſt vertuouſe byſſhop / in whiche he gyueth iugemente by expreſſe and playne wordes / that it is agaynſt ſcrypture &amp; our relygion / that y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of chriſt ar had in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of chriſten men / wherof we may gather euidently that in this mater / bothe Ierome &amp; alſo other biſſhops were of the ſame mynde that Epiphanius was of. Herfore Euſebius<note place="margin">Euſebiꝰ</note> alſo reherſeth / as a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge &amp; an vnwont thyng / that in Ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarea Philippi (in which cyte the woman was borne / whom Chriſt healed from the fluxe of blode) He dyd ſe two ymages of braſſe / the one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woman / thother of chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:23564:31"/> our ſauyour / whiche ymages yet were ſet vp at churche dores / nat in the churche ſelfe / as the ſame Euſebius recordeth. And at the laſt / he ſayth thus: It is no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyle if thoſe perſones of the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles which dyd beleue / were ſene for ſuche benefytes as they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of the ſauyour / to offre as you wolde ſaye / ſuche a maner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde or recompenſe / ſyth it is ſo that we do ſee ymages &amp; tables of the apoſtles Peter &amp; Paule / &amp; alſo of Chriſt our ſauyour to be carue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and paynted / euen theſe daies alſo we haue ſene moreouer olde yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of them kepte of certayne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones / which thinge me thinke is obſerued / according to the cuſtom of the gentyles / without any dyffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence / bycauſe they ar wont in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wiſe to honour them / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they thought worthye of honoure. For
<pb facs="tcp:23564:31"/> that the armes or ymages of olde men are reſerued &amp; kepte for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance to them that ſhal come after: it is a ſygne &amp; token both of their honoure / &amp; alſo of theſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes loue towardꝭ the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Li. vii. ca. 14.</note> Thus ſaith Euſebius in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eccliaſtical hiſtori.</p>
            <p>¶ Herof we doo eaſely perceyue / that the images whiche Euſebius dyd ſe / were ſet vp / nat within the churches / but at the churche dores. Agayne / nat to thentente that they ſhuld be honoured / but rather that they ſhuld be a teſtymony &amp; record how great honour they were to be iudged worthy of / whoſe images were reſerued &amp; kepte: all whiche thynges neuertheleſſe / Euſebius doth nat hyde / to haue taken their begynnynge of the Gentyles and hethen people. But what thinke you that he wolde haue ſayd / if he had ſene ymages ſet vp i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> churches
<pb facs="tcp:23564:32"/> and no leſſe worſhipped of chriſten men / than euer they were of anye gentyls / which thyng (a lacke for petye) it is vndouted both to haue be done: ye / &amp; to be done euen now at theſe dayes alſo. Of theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges therfore we may gather what is the cauſe / why the olde fathers dyd write nothynge agaynſt ſuch maner of ymages. For there was no man at that tyme / which dyd ſo moche as ones dreme / that euer ſo gret a multytude of images ſhuld crepe into churches / as hath crope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in / for as moche as they knewe it to be forbydden with ſo open &amp; euy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent oracles &amp; teſtymonyes of the ſcrypture. But agaynſte the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Gentyles / a man ſhall fynde many thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges written by the fathers very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyngly &amp; eloquent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / bycauſe the ſuperſtityon of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd raygne euery where eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the
<pb facs="tcp:23564:32"/> ſame tyme / in which thoſe holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were lyuynge. yea / &amp; was defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the gentyles with the ſame weapens / with which both in our tyme / &amp; alſo in the tyme of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers / certayne chriſten men haue gone about to defende and mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne their ymages. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer thynge Lactantyus wrote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the ydoles of the gentyles / we may by very good right apply the ſame agaynſt our ymages: all beit in his tyme (as we haue ſayd) they wer nat yet vſed among cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten men.<note place="margin">Lacta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiꝰ</note> Amonge manye places it lyketh me at this tyme to allege one.<note place="margin">Lib. ij, cap, ij.</note> For thus he demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth of the gentyles: If you do therfore fere your goddes / bicauſe you do iuge them to be in heuen: why doo you nat than lyfte vp youre eyes in to heuen? why do you rather loke to walles / to ſtockes / &amp; ſtones: than
<pb facs="tcp:23564:33"/> to that place / where you do beleue that they be? This ſame queſtion in lyke maner may we demaunde of our ſuperſtityouſe chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men: If they do beleue that god &amp; ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ar in heuen: why doo they nat rather lyfte vp theire eyes to that place / than to the deed ymages? But let vs here alſo Athanaſe / wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng in this wyſe agaynſt the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyls.<note place="margin">Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</note> Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay (I beſech you) howe or after what maner god is knowen by images: whether is it by the mater &amp; ſtuffe put rounde a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout them: or els is it by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhape and facion brought i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſtuffe? If it be for the ſtuffe of the images that he is knowen / than what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth any ſhape or facion to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught in by the workeman? &amp; why dyd nat god appere as well by all maner of ſtuffe / before that any y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages were made: ſyth all thingꝭ
<pb facs="tcp:23564:33"/> do wytneſſe his glorie. But if the ſhape and facyon brought into the ſtuffe / be the cauſe of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of god: what nedeth than any payntynge / or any other ſtuffe at all? and why is nat god knowen rather by the very lyue creatures / whoſe ſhapes or ymages? for dout<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les the glori of god ſhuld be more clerely &amp; euydently knowen / if it wer ſhewed by the lyue creatures both reſonable &amp; vnreſonable / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by deed &amp; vnmoueable creatures. Therefore whan you do graue or paynte ymages / for the entente to haue vnderſtandynge &amp; knowlege of god: forſoth you do an vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy &amp; an vnmete thinge. &amp;c. Now Athanaſius wold neuer haue pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed in his mynde / to write any ſuche maner thynge agaynſte the gentyles / if he had ſene the chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men of his tyme / entangled and
<pb facs="tcp:23564:34"/> wrapped in ſuche ſuperſtityon of ymages / as we do ſe a great parte of the worlde to be pytuouſly ſnar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led now in our tyme: but he wold rather haue exercyſed his penne a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſt chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men / if they had ben lyke our cryſten men now adayes. But nothynge letteth / but that we may very accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly apply y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thingꝭ agaynſt our ſuperſtityous chriſten men: for they pretende the ſame cauſe of hauyng images / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which Athanaſius reherſeth / that the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyles were moued / that is to wit / that by images they maye be put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of god: which thynge / ſyth the creatures of god (whether we do conſider the ſtuffe or the ſhape &amp; facyon of them) may do moch more ſtrongly (as Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius iugeth full wel) there is no nede that we ſhuld ronne vnto the workes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which do repreſent
<pb facs="tcp:23564:34"/> but onely I wot nat what falſe y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage vnto vs. For whom ſoeuer trees / ſtones / ſyluer / golde / &amp; other ſtuffe / wherof ymages are made / fynally whom the ſyght of man / to whom god hath gyuen lyfe &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon / can nat ſtyre nor put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of god: ſurely images ſhal natte ſtyre vp that man with anye frute or profyte: for they (as Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen writeth agaynſt Selſus) doo rather plucke awaye the memorie of man from god / &amp; do tourne the eyes of the mynde bacwardes / to behold &amp; conſyder erthly thinges. For euery man knoweth / that the more nere that one thynge reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth another in nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie / ſo moche the more ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it doth renewe the remembraun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce in vs of that thynge / to whom it is lyke. For trees or ſtones do more ſurely and lyuely putte vs in
<pb facs="tcp:23564:35"/> remembraunce of god / whan they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydered of vs / hauyng their owne naturall ſhape &amp; facyon / ſo as they were fyrſt created of god: than whan by the worke and craft of men beynge beryued of theire owne naturall ſhape / they doo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe &amp; reſemble vnto vs the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and lykeneſſe of man / or of any other thynge. For ſoner ſhall the remembraunce come to thy mynde of the Caruer or Paynter / whoſe workmanſhip thou doſt marueyle at / than the remembrance of god / the creatour &amp; maker of all thingꝭ. It is therfore nothynge els but a pure diſceyte of the deuyll / which calleth vs from the praiſynge and charytable louynge of the lyue y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of god / vnto deed ymages of wood or ſtone / which ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a folyſſhe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfaiter of god / hath folyſſhlye carnen or paynted. We
<pb facs="tcp:23564:35"/> coulde alſo allege manye other te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtymonyes oute of the writynges of the fathers: but it ſhulde be all in vayne / to recyte any mo to him whiche is nat moued with theſe / which we haue all redy reherſed.</p>
            <p>¶ Here we haue thoughte it very expedyent &amp; neceſſary to declare &amp; make playne / accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to the truth of hyſtories / whan / &amp; by what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynners ymages begane to come vp amonge Chriſten men: &amp; who agayne on the other ſyde did their endeuour to put them downe / and with how moche buſyneſſe / &amp; how great ieoperdy / good &amp; well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed men haue attempted this thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vntyll the church was brought in to this preſent condityon &amp; ſtate of thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges fallyng ſtyl apece to worſe and worſe. Vndoutedly the lawes as well of the chriſten emperours / as of the chriſten counſels / made
<pb facs="tcp:23564:36"/> agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt ymagꝭ / came tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fyrſt forth whan through the ſlouthfulneſſe &amp; neglygence of byſſhoppes &amp; their vayne curyouſe deſyre to wyn the fauour of god / nat only images &amp; pyctures crepte into the churches / but alſo (which is wont comunely to chaunce) they began to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped of the peple. We rede that Serenus / the byſſhoppe of Maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſilia<note place="margin">Serenꝰ Byſſhop of Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilia,</note> / a very holy man / was ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed &amp; toke it ſo greuouſly (as mete was) that ymages were ſet vp in churches: that he dyd caſte down all the ymages at ones whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che were in his churche / dyd breke them / &amp; at the laſte dyd alſo burne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We do nat deny / but that this dede of Serenus was ſore rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of Gregorie / which was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gregorius magnus<note place="margin">Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnus,</note> / &amp; that the ſeyde Serenus was admoniſhed &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelled of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeid Gregori / that
<pb facs="tcp:23564:36"/> he ſhulde nat forbyd or let images to be had: but that he ſhuld teche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honouring of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any wiſe to be auoyded. But what other thynge ſhuld the ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dredberer of relygio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vertue fallyng in decay / do in this mater / as well as in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? For about that tyme the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of Rome beganne to thretten / and gyue lykelyhod of gret ruyne of the fayth afterwardꝭ to folowe.</p>
            <p>¶ But amonge the Grekes / Leo themperour / the .iii.<note place="margin">Leo Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peroure of the Grekes.</note> of that name / a man both well learned / and alſo vertuouſe and godly (he raygned in the yere of our lorde .vii. C.lx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xxiiii) diſtroied al images vniuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſally / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Gregori the .iii of that name by his letters / that he ſhuld do the ſame thinge lykewyſe at Rome.<note place="margin">Gregory the third</note> But this Gregorie nat onely refuſed to be obedyent to the emperours co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / but alſo
<pb facs="tcp:23564:37"/> at Rauenna was the authour &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynner of ſedition / to which cytie he called a certayne menye of byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes &amp; made a counſel / in whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he decreed agaynſte thempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement / that images ought to be had in moche more ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noure / than euer they were before.</p>
            <p>And to the entente that he might the moore boldely inſtytute thys thynge agaynſt themperour with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oute any punyſſhmente: nat very longe before / he had gone aboute traytorouſly to forſake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour / and to fall vnto the parte of the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che kynge. After the deth of Leo / Conſtantyne his ſonne / the fyfth of that name / wyllyng to confyrme his fathers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement &amp; decre / called togyther all the lerned men and byſſhoppes / oute of all Grece lande / beyng in no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre.<note place="margin">Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tin the. v</note> CCC.xxx. which comparyng the ſcryptures
<pb facs="tcp:23564:37"/> to the reaſons of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell / which we ſpake of before / called by Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie: determyned with one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent That it is nat lauful to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which by chriſt do beleue in god / to haue any images / either of the creator / or the creatures to honour theym: but rather of the ieoperdyes of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſyons / that they were all to be taken away at ones. So to the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynnynge of Leo / Conſtantyne his ſonne / and all his ſucceſſoures dyd cleue &amp; abyde by it: vntyll ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che tyme / that the cruell woman Hirene<note place="margin">Hiren.</note> went about that horryble and excedynge wicked tragedye / whereof we ſhall ſpeke / nat longe hereafter. But the decrees of that wycked woman / were vertuouſly abrogated by Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantynes ſonne / the ſyxte of that name. There co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth nowe happely to my mynde / the decre of Theodoſius &amp; Valens
<pb facs="tcp:23564:38"/> whiche Petrus Crinitus / a man that had red many thynges / doth recyte in the .ix. boke / De honeſta diſciplina. His own very wordes I ſhall faythfully &amp; truly reherſe.</p>
            <p>Valens &amp; Theodoſius the noble emperours wrot to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> officer called Prefectus pretorius:<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Theodo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſius and Valens.</note> Foraſmoch as our dilygent ſtudy &amp; care is / in all thingꝭ to maynteyne &amp; vphold the faith &amp; honour of god: we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid any maner ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to graue or ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke the image of chriſt our ſauyour of ſtone / of wood / or of any other ſtuffe / orels to paynte the ſame w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> colours. yea / and wherſoeuer any ſuch ymage be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that it be taken awaye / and they ſore punyſſhed / who ſo euer ſhall attempte any thynge contrarye to our decrees and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement / in whiche thynge if anye man do requyre an authoure: let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:23564:38"/> the decrees and commandemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of Emperoures / whiche haue ben collected and gathered by a ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyre of the righte connynge men Trybunianus / Baſylydes / The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophilus / Dioſcorus / and other at the commaundement of the mooſt noble Emperoure Iuſtiniane.</p>
            <p>Thus farre ſaythe Crinitus:</p>
            <p>It is therfore euydente and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſt / that themperours alſo whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che were before the tyme of Leo / dydde dilygentlye prouyde / that the ſuperſtityon of Images ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de natte by anye manner meanes pollute and defyle the churches of Chriſten men.<note place="margin">Pontiꝰ paulinꝰ Byſſhop of Nola the fyrſt cauſer that ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges wer paynted.</note> The fyrſte of all other (as far as we can gather of hiſtories) which did cauſe images to be paynted in churches: was Pontius Paulinus byſſhoppe of Nola / about the yere of our lorde ecccl. For he ſolemnyſing yerely
<pb facs="tcp:23564:39"/> the byrthe daye of Saynt Felix / was wonte to make a great and a coſtly feſt vnto the churche / and to thentent that they whiche ſate at the ſeyd feſt / ſhulde be the ſooner and more eaſely prouoked to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce / &amp; to the conſyderatyon of godlye thinges: he paynted on the churche walles / ymages of the hiſtores of the old teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhulde haue ſomwhat alſo where with they mighte fede / and delyte their eyes frutefully. Afore this Paulinus / you ſhall nat lyghtly fynde / that any ſuche thynge was attempted by any man / at the leſt wyſe / beyng of any famous memo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye. For in ſuche wyſe by lytell &amp; lytell / this ſuperſtityo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt nedes crepe in: lykewyſe as other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges did / which haue corrupted the puryte &amp; prefection of the churche. Nowe who is he / that dothe nat
<pb facs="tcp:23564:39"/> perceyue and ſe / that Paulynus dyd two maner waies offende. for fyrſt agaynſte the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of ſaynte Paule / he was bolde / &amp; toke vpon him ſelfe to make open feſtes in the churche. And (which agayne was as great an offence / and ſuche as can nat be excuſed) he began with ymages to exhorte men vnto the loue &amp; exerciſynge of temperaunce: whan he beynge a chriſten man / ought rather to haue gone about to do the ſame w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctryne and good example. Wherfore it doth euidently appere that this byſſhoppe dyd in no wiſe begyn that thynge of a pure godly ſpiryte: but if a man do well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydre &amp; way euery thinge / he ſhall fynde / that with the ſame ſpyrite / that is to wytte moſt retcheleſſe / &amp; diſpiſyng of godly thinges / other men alſo haue taken vpon them to
<pb facs="tcp:23564:40"/> defende imagꝭ. For the popes &amp; biſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhops (I wot nat whether throgh euyll wyll or els through a certayn pride) began with toth &amp; nayle to defende the vſe / or rather the abuſe of ymages agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the greke empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours: vntyll ſuche tyme as by the labour &amp; helpe of Hyrenes<note place="margin">Herene empreſſe</note> (which after the deceſſe of Leo her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule &amp; gouerna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pyre many yeres) a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel was aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled at Nice / in whiche cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell ſhe cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed to be abrogated &amp; dyſanulled / whatſoeuer was before decreed by Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyne / concernyng the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge away of ymages. Neither coulde this wyckedneſſe ſuffyſe &amp; content her mynde: but ſhe did cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe the bodye of Conſtantyne to be digged vp agayne out of the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to be brente to aſſhes / &amp; laſte of all to be throwen into the ſee.</p>
            <p>¶ This very ſame Hyrene / after
<pb facs="tcp:23564:40"/> that ſhe was by her ſonne depoſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous empire / lefte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vnaſſaid nor neuer reſted vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll by abhominable &amp; traytorous craftes / ſhe wan agayn the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pire vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to her ſelfe: which thing whan ſhe had brought to paſſe / accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to her owne mynde / ſhe dyd caſte her ſonne in to priſon / plucked out his eyes / &amp; in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion ſlewe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo. But whan ſhe feared that her tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſhulde nat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue nor laſt lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſhe made labours (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope of Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e beyng broker &amp; ſpokeſman) to be maried vnto Charles the great / o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe called Charlemayn / ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of France: &amp; for this cauſe ſhe ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue lycence to the byſſhop of Rome to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate the crown of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pire of Rome vnto Charles / hopyng ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily that her owne tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny ſhuld be ſafe / if by tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlatyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pire of the Grekes traytourouſly vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemen
<pb facs="tcp:23564:41"/>
/ ſhe dyd bynde / nat onely Charles / but alſo the biſſhoppe of Rome / &amp; make theym her frendes with this great benefyte.</p>
            <p>¶ But whan Nicephorus,<note place="margin">Nicepho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rus.</note> which than was capitayne of the army of the Grekes perceyued theſe traito<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rouſe diſceytes / forthw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in all haſt he did caſt Hirene i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as ſhe had deſerued / in which ſhe made a wretched ende / &amp; changed this lyfe with deth / worthy &amp; mete for ſuche goodly actꝭ as ſhe had done.<note place="margin">O cruell woman,</note> This ſame Hirene which digged vp the deed body of her father in lawe / &amp; brent it. Which put out her owne ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes eyes / &amp; ſlewe him in priſon: which betraied themperour of the Grekes: &amp; this ſame biſſhoppe / the counſeller &amp; helper of the moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked &amp; vngratiouſe woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes &amp; enforceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: which biſſhop toke awaye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the right &amp; lawfull
<pb facs="tcp:23564:41"/> emperour his empier / &amp; did put in another into thempier who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe: but yet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / that he hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe ſhuld haue Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me / &amp; Italye for his parte: This worſhipful couple (Iſai) auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced ymages vnto this eſtymation &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nonour. For whatſoeuer ymages or pictures are in eſtimation: they may nat w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out good cauſe thanke theſe .ii. for it / as fyrſt begynners. Howbeit / the ſucceſſoures alſo of Charles / dyd afterwardꝭ their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t endeuour to maynteyne &amp; vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hold theſe abhominations: leſt the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation &amp; ground worke of ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye / which Charles had layde / ſhuld haue lacked building to gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſſhe it full of all impyetie &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes. Howbeit thoſe men in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes paſt / dyd neuer than pollute &amp; defyle temples &amp; churches with ſo many images / &amp; ſhewing ſo many
<pb facs="tcp:23564:42"/> feſt apperance of ydolatry (which thinge we may perceyue &amp; ſe euen yet by thoſe which they bylded) as haue ben ſet vp eueriwher in theſe laſte .C. yeres / to the occaſyon of moſt vaine honour: which honour to thentent to make it the more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted with falſe &amp; lieng wonders he ſtyred vp &amp; moued ſuꝑſtitiouſe perſones in euery place / to begyn pylgrymages to ſuche ymages / to their gret hynderance / both of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / &amp; of faythe &amp; godlyneſſe, For (I praye you) tell me what other thynge ſhall a man fynde in ſuche maner churches of the bleſſed vyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin: than certayne fylthy &amp; ſmoky ymages? For god (ſuch is his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedyng goodneſſe) leſte any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of ydolatry ſhuld be left vnto men: he wolde that the body of the bleſſed virgin ſhuld nat be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Likewiſe as he did by the body of
<pb facs="tcp:23564:42"/> Moſes. We wyl ſay nothing here of the ymages of ſaynte Anne / of ſayntes / nor of the images of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: which men with lyke ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtityon / haue begon to ſet vp wel-nere in euery corner / &amp; to worſhyp them. And (which is as gret a fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhnes as may be) whan there ar ſo many images ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes in one church: to one they do gyue I wot nat what power of workynge my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles / to the great hynderaunce &amp; contempte of all the reſydue. Bref<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / ſo gret is the vanyte of images that though i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very dede thei could put vs in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of god: yet neuertheleſſe for dyuerſe occaſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of offenſyons &amp; ydolatrye / it were expedient &amp; neceſſari to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taken awaye in all the haſt / ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the example of Eſechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the moſt holy kyng / whiche did caſt down &amp; breke the braſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / 
<pb facs="tcp:23564:43"/> which was ſet vp by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of god: whan he had parcey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that it was worſhypped con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god.</p>
            <p>Theſe thynges / which we haue hytherto recyted / if he that fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the glori of Chriſt / wyll dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently way &amp; conſyder i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mynd he ſhall vndoubtedly perceyue / that whatſoeuer ymages ar honoured in churches / or anye maner waye maye be honoured: neither ought / neither may be ſuffred amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / vnleſſe we wyl do againſt the manifeſt precepte of god / &amp; deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyſe &amp; ſet at nought both the faith and alſo the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtels martyrs / and alſo of holy fathers. Fynally except we can fynde in o<hi rend="sup">r</hi> herte in the ſtede of the lawes / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made both by chriſten emperours / &amp; alſo counſels to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the traditions of the biſſhop
<pb facs="tcp:23564:43"/> of Rome / &amp; of the moſt wycked wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / whoſe delyte &amp; pleſure both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / was in traiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / robbries / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuall ſtudy to deuide &amp; diſtroy the</p>
            <p>¶ Fynally as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g (empire, the takyng down &amp; putting away of altres / the which haue knowen the wicked abuſyons of the maſſe / may &amp; wyll be ſone ſatiſfied &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any gret buſynes / they which do nat know / can nat be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed with moch buſynes: vnleſſe thei be taught firſt / how gret abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mination y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe is in the ſight of god. Therfore this one thinge we deſyre to be conſydered of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fere &amp; drede god / in what maner &amp; forwhat ende &amp; ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / chriſt our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour did i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitute his holy ſouper Truly to thentent / that this diſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples (that is to ſay / they which wil lyue accordinglye to his doctryne and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement) aſſemblynge
<pb facs="tcp:23564:44"/> togyther / ſhuld take that miſticall breed &amp; miſticall drinke in comen / &amp; eueryone put other in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of that incomparable charytie of chriſt / by which he ſuffred doth for their ſaluation: &amp; by the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of / their fayth &amp; truſt in god bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge encreaſed / ſhuld be enflamed both with the hatred of ſines / &amp; alſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue of all vertues / profeſſyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be one body &amp; one breed in Chriſt. By this meanes onely / holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar nouryſſhed with chriſt the meate of lyfe. Now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to theſe thingꝭ / that which is done co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly in maſſes. Maſſes moſt ſpecyally ar done for the belyes ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke: or els at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſtwiſe to purchaſe ſome merite afore god / which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelfe alone / although al this buſynes were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by god / ſhuld yet make it abhomynable to god. Beſydes this / there ar ſayd &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:23564:44"/> done ſo many thinges / whiche do turne away our myndes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt which raigneth in heuen / vnto the worke of the preſt. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereth no doctryne or exhorta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon in their mother tongue / that they miȝt be edifyed therby. Ther is no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion had / although the wordes whiche the preſt reherſeth do make mentyon of it. And why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les the preeſt alone dothe receyue the breed &amp; the cuppe of the lorde: there is natte / as Paule ſayth / the ſouper of the lorde repreſented. There ar ſayd alſo many thinges which ar playne repugnant to the ſcripture: for they do teche to truſt vnto the merytes &amp; interceſſyon of ſaintes. And (which thing is moſt highly to be abhorred) where as the oblation of Chriſt (by whiche only beyng made vpon the croſſe / we ar aſſoiled &amp; ſanctified for euer
<pb facs="tcp:23564:45"/> more) ought to be preached: The preſt boſteth / that as ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes as he doth his maſſe / ſo oftentimes he doth offre Chriſt to his father / and therfore doth by it obtayne the put<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng away of all euyls / &amp; a hepe of al good thinges to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only / which by gyuyng any thinge to the preſt do make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues partakers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe / by the / reaſon wherof it is come to paſſe / that ſo many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / al care of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cye layde aparte / do hope that heuen ſhalbe opened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / euen by maſſes alone. Who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer acknowlegeth the lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus as our only ſauyour &amp; ſancty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyer / if he do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder theſe thinges dilygently / &amp; with the ſame do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thoſe thingꝭ / which our lorde both ſayd &amp; dyd: and beſydes that / dyd betake to vs for to be reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / &amp; ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times put in vſe: he ſhal eſely perceyue &amp; ſe / that there was
<pb facs="tcp:23564:45"/> neuer anye ſuperſtityon in tymes paſt / which had in it ſelfe ſo great impyetie &amp; wickedneſſe / ſo gret co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempte of god / ſo gret diſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all vertues / as hathe the maſſe / ſo as it hath ben vſed to be had nowe theſe certayne yeres. And hereof wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he knoweth / that nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is ſo moch to be hated &amp; abhorred of cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: he ſhall ꝑceyue that all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of it is vtterly to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away: &amp; therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alters / which were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forgers of ſuch ydolatry / &amp; in dede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rich wyues of preſtꝭ but very hurtfull to all cryſten people wer in no wyſe to be ſuffred of that gouernour &amp; ruler / which princy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to execute his offyce to the honour &amp; pleaſure of chriſt. Let criſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know the truth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater / &amp; than afterwardꝭ let them</p>
            <p>Laſt of all / this thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g alſo (iuge. is to be obſerued in this matter / 
<pb facs="tcp:23564:46"/> though neuer ſo gret offenſyons &amp; occaſyons of euyls come through pyctures &amp; images / that yet for all that / it is nat laufull for any man but the hed offycer &amp; ruler to caſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out / namely out of open &amp; come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> places. For in aſmoche as they are outward thingꝭ / no man ought to take vpon hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more power ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> than the condition &amp; ſtate of euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall requyre / that it is to wit / that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priuatly banyſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of his owne mynde / reiecti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> folyſhe eſtimation of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now to an houſholder it belongeth / accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Iames the patriarch<note place="margin">Iames the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarche.</note> / to clenſe &amp; rid his houſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But to caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches &amp; comen places / is the duty of the hedofficer &amp; gouernour / which duty (thanke be to Chriſt) our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour hath knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; hath execu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted with cryſten grauyte. And one
<pb facs="tcp:23564:46"/> thyng is to be eſchewed in this bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynes / lykewiſe as in al other / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che it belongeth to criſten mennes charge for to do (&amp; it is the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell of. S. Paule) that we do nat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traye &amp; ſet forth our good to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll wordꝭ of men: &amp; that the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g which was inſtytuted to the helth and ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many men / be nat an occaſyon of hurte to any man. Wherfore if any man in diſtroye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of ymages / ſhulde do any thynge preſumputouſly / outragyouſly / &amp; paſt the meſure of charite / he ſhuld bynde hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe by ſo moch to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more greuouſe ſine / by howe moche the thynge is more holy / in whiche he foloweth his owne ſenſuall luſt / &amp; the offycer ought (nat w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out good cauſe) to punyſſhe him for breki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of loue &amp; charite. Alſo it ought nat to be aſcribed to any outragiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe / though vnſenſyble ymages
<pb facs="tcp:23564:47"/> be nat ſo ſoftely &amp; ſo tenderly han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled / as certayn me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (through a fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ymaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as though w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fygure &amp; ſymilytude of man / they had alſo mannes wyttes &amp; reaſon) are wont to haue compaſſyon / and to ſorowe ſomwhat whan they ar broken. For if we were dyſpoſed to take awaye images / after ſuche maner and facyon as ſcripture te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth / whiche fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon doutleſſe muſt nedes be beſt: we ought to breke them / yea / and that all to pouder / that they might neuer be made whole agayne / nor be reſtored into ſo wycked an vſe in whiche we ought nat to haue ſo gretly regarded the labour &amp; craft of man / ſyth it is our duty to offre euen oure owne ſelues alſo to the croſſe / and to all maner afflyction / rather than to be wyllynge to gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue occaſyon of fallynge to any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:23564:47"/> that walketh in the waye of vertue and godlyneſſe. And wolde god there were in all men as moch care and dilygence to make moche of / and to beware of offendynge or hurtynge the verye lyue ymages / whiche god him ſelfe hathe made to his owne lykeneſſe: as we doo ſee to be in very manye men / that thoſe deed &amp; dombe ymages ſhuld nat be hardlye / nor vnreuerently entreated. To conlude ſhortlye to plucke downe ymages and pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures / and to ryd them quyte oute of churches / is an holy thynge / and ought to be begon accordyng to the commaundemente of god, It is conuenyente therefore and mete / that it be performed and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fylled in ſuche wyſe / that it maye be accepted and alowed of all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtye god. That is to wytte / 
<pb facs="tcp:23564:48"/> that they be ſo taken away / that there be no whytte of them remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge / namely to lyke vſe / and alſo that yet neuertheles / nothinge be done <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſumptuouſely / nor out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragyouſely / nothynge that maye gyue anye man good cauſe to be troubled: but that all thynges be done charytably / of pure and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte loue / and deſyre to do profyte to all men. And after this facyon god graunte that his people maye be delyuered from ydoles and ymages / throughout the whole world / fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tone ende to the tother.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Printed for W. Marſhall. With the Kynges mooſt gratiouſe priuylege.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23564:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
